<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Hugo Academic CV Theme</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/</link>
      <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Hugo Academic CV Theme</description>
    <generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 24 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>http://localhost:1313/media/icon_hu_645fa481986063ef.png</url>
      <title>Hugo Academic CV Theme</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>How was my week (May 12-18)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/post/last_week_12_05/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/post/last_week_12_05/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The end of the school year is approaching and this is my last news post. All the time we are either writing tests and tests, or preparing for them.The hardest thing is to sit and wait for the results. But I hope that there will be A&amp;rsquo;s in non-core subjects, of the stories only in the basic History of Russia, I have exactly 5, the rest is unclear&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The session is close and I hope that I will close everything well)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Markup languages. LaTeX.</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/post/latex/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/post/latex/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;markup-languages-latex&#34;&gt;Markup languages. LaTeX.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;▌Introduction&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In today&amp;rsquo;s world, where information is everywhere, not only its essence is important, but also how it is presented. This is where markup languages come to the rescue. They allow you to give the text structure, format it for easy perception and make it compatible with various platforms. In this report, we will look at the concept of markup languages in general and delve into the study of one of the most powerful and respected representatives of this class – LaTeX.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;,What is a markup language?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A markup language is a notation system used to add additional information to a text about its structure, formatting, and semantics. Unlike visual editors like WYSIWYG (&amp;ldquo;What You See Is What You Get&amp;rdquo;), markup languages use text commands (tags or special characters) to specify the desired appearance of the document. Subsequently, a special program (compiler or interpreter) processes this marked-up text and converts it into a final format, for example, HTML, PDF or DOCX.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Key features of markup languages:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;• Text format: Easy to read and edit with a regular text editor.
• Platform independence: Can be processed on different operating systems.
• Clear separation of content and presentation: The content remains clean and easily modifiable, while the markup defines its appearance.
• Automation capability: Allows you to automate the process of formatting and generating documents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Examples of markup languages:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;• HTML (HyperText Markup Language): The main language for creating web pages.
• XML (Extensible Markup Language): A universal language for representing data.
Markdown: A lightweight and simple markup language for writing text documents, often used for documentation, README files, and online articles.
LaTeX: A markup language especially popular in scientific circles for creating complex documents with formulas, graphs, and bibliographies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;LaTeX: The magic of precise typography&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;LaTeX (pronounced &amp;ldquo;Latech&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;Latex&amp;rdquo;) is a markup language based on TeX, developed by Leslie Lamport in the 1980s. It is designed to create professional-quality documents, especially in scientific and technical fields. LaTeX has exceptional capabilities for formatting mathematical formulas, managing bibliographies, creating complex tables and graphs, and structuring large documents such as books and dissertations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Advantages of LaTeX:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;• High-quality typography: LaTeX provides exceptional text and formula display quality, making documents pleasant to read and professional-looking.
• Automated formatting: LaTeX takes over most of the routine formatting work, such as section numbering, creating a table of contents and bibliography.
• Exceptional math capabilities: LaTeX has a powerful command set for complex mathematical formulas, equations, and symbols.
• Bibliography Management: LaTeX makes it easy to manage bibliographic data using files.bib and automatically generate literature lists in various styles.
• Support for extensions (packages): The large number of available packages allows you to extend the functionality of LaTeX and adapt it to specific needs.
• Stability and reliability: LaTeX is a mature and well–tested markup language used worldwide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Disadvantages of LaTeX:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;• Steeper learning curve: Compared to WYSIWYG editors, LaTeX requires some time to learn syntax and commands.
• Not WYSIWYG: You don&amp;rsquo;t see the formatting result during the writing process. It is necessary to compile the document to view the changes.
• More difficult debugging: Syntax errors can be difficult to debug, especially for beginners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;LaTeX code example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;\documentclass{article}
\usepackage{amsmath}&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;\title{The Pythagorean Theorem}
\author{Your Name}
\date{\today}&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;\begin{document}
\maketitle&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;\section{Introduction}
In geometry, the Pythagorean theorem establishes the relationship between the sides of a right triangle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;\section{Statement of the theorem}
In a right-angled triangle, the square of the length of the hypotenuse is equal to the sum of the squares of the lengths of the legs.  Mathematically, this can be written as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;\begin{equation}
a&lt;sup&gt;2 + b&lt;/sup&gt;2 = c^2
\end{equation}&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where $a$ and $b$ are the lengths of the legs, and $c$ is the length of the hypotenuse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;\end{document}&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;• defines the type of document (article).
• downloads a package for working with mathematical formulas.
• , , set the title, author, and date.
• \begin(document) and \end(document) restrict the beginning and end of the document.
•&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;§ (&amp;hellip;)
defines the section headings.
• \begin(equation) and \end(equation) are used to display the mathematical formula in a separate line.
• It is used to display mathematical symbols inside the text.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tools for working with LaTeX:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;• Text editors: VS Code (with extensions), TeXstudio, Sublime Text (with extensions), Atom (with extensions).
• LaTeX distributions: MiKTeX (Windows), TeX Live (Linux, macOS), MacTeX (macOS).
• LaTeX online editors: Overleaf, ShareLaTeX (now part of Overleaf), Papeeria.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;,LaTeX application areas&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;LaTeX is widely used in the following areas:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;• Scientific publications: Articles, books, dissertations, reports.
• Technical documentation: User manuals, specifications, instructions.
• Mathematical and engineering documents: Textbooks, laboratory work, reports.
• Slide creation: Using the Beamer package, you can create professional-looking presentations.
• Typography: LaTeX is used to create books, magazines and other printed products.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;▌Conclusion&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Markup languages play an important role in creating structured and well-formatted documents. LaTeX, as one of the most powerful and flexible markup languages, provides tools for creating professional-quality documents, especially in areas where precise typography and complex mathematical formulas are required. Despite some difficulty in mastering, LaTeX pays off the effort due to the high quality and capabilities it provides. For those who work with science, technology, or just appreciate the impeccable appearance of documents, LaTeX will become an indispensable tool.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How was my week (May 05-11)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/post/last_week_05_05/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/post/last_week_05_05/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The week of June 05-11 passed quite calmly. There were few classes (as well as people in them). I worked on the weekend, and on the 9th we watched the parade in the morning, and in the evening we tried to go and watch the fireworks, but it turned out that he wasn&amp;rsquo;t with us, but we watched it anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And on Sunday, 11.05, my best friend&amp;rsquo;s birthday was, we went to play on D&amp;amp;D, and I was the only one who died there(. The photo shows my character, a Black Lady. We had a good time.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Scientific Programming Languages</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/post/langs/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/post/langs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this article, we will talk about scientific programming and which languages are best used for working in science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-is-scientific-programming&#34;&gt;What is scientific programming?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scientific programming is a highly oriented programming style for scientific calculations. It is distinguished from other types of programming by the extreme correctness and stability of the final product, the strict separation of scientific and interface parts, the individuality of algorithms, and the predominance of efficiency over versatility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where is scientific programming applied?   Scientific programming is at the core of any modern global research. All advanced technologies, from quantum computers to space programs, would not be possible without scientific programming specialists who can provide scientists with a reliable and accurate tool for making discoveries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A number of branches of science directly depend on the level of development of scientific programming. So, unmanned vehicles, &amp;ldquo;smart&amp;rdquo; management systems for urban and agricultural enterprises, stock exchanges, robotics, genetic engineering, artificial intelligence that surpasses human capabilities are waiting for their fulfillment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scientific programming languages&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Different existing programming languages can be used in different fields, but in this article I want to talk about three.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;1-r&#34;&gt;1. R&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;R, which is a direct descendant of the older programming language S, was released back in 1995 and has been improving ever since. Written in languages such as C and Fortran, this project is currently supported by the R Foundation for Statistical Computing. An excellent set of high-quality, open-source domain-specific packages. R has packages at its disposal for almost any quantitative and statistical application imaginable. This includes neural networks, nonlinear regression, phylogenetics, building complex diagrams, graphs, and much, much more. Along with the basic installation, we also have the option to install extensive built-in functions and methods. In addition, R handles matrix algebra data perfectly.R is a powerful language that has a huge selection of applications for statistical data collection and data visualization, and the fact that it is an open source software allows it to gather a large number of fans among developers. It is due to its effectiveness for the initial purposes that this programming language has managed to achieve wide popularity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;2-python&#34;&gt;2. Python&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Python is one of the most popular programming languages at the moment. It has a simple syntax and a wide variety of libraries and frameworks that will help you achieve the desired task.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Python is a good option for data science purposes, and this statement is true for both beginner and advanced levels of work in this field. Much of data science is centered around the ETL (extract-transform-load) process. This feature makes Python an ideal programming language for such purposes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;3-julia&#34;&gt;3. Julia&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Released just over 5 years ago, Julia has made an impression on the world of computational methods. The language has achieved such popularity due to the fact that several large organizations, including some in the financial industry, almost immediately began using it for their own purposes. Julia is a compiled JIT (just–in-time) language that allows you to achieve good performance. This language is quite simple, it provides the possibilities of dynamic typing and scripting of an interpreted language such as Python. Julia was designed for numerical analysis, and it can also be considered a general-purpose programming language. Of course, this language has its drawbacks, the main one being its youth. This language does not have enough software packages yet, but in a few years it will be able to compete with its main competitors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scientific programming and the languages in which it can be used are gaining unprecedented popularity due to the progress that is taking place in our society. It allows scientists to develop technologies and transform our world into the “world of the future.”&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Working with bibliography</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/post/bibtex/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/post/bibtex/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;working-with-bibliography-a-guide-for-researchers-and-writers&#34;&gt;Working with Bibliography: A Guide for Researchers and Writers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A bibliography is a systematic list of sources used in the creation of a scientific paper, article, book, or any other text claiming academic value. It plays a key role in academic integrity, allows readers to verify your statements, and serves as a valuable resource for further research. The purpose of this report is to provide practical guidance on how to work effectively with a bibliography, including its creation, formatting, and use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;why-do-i-need-a-bibliography&#34;&gt;Why do I need a bibliography?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bibliography performs several important functions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Academic integrity and plagiarism prevention: By identifying sources, you acknowledge the contributions of other authors to your work and avoid accusations of plagiarism.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Support your arguments: The bibliography allows readers to verify your claims and verify their validity by providing evidence from other sources.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Contextualizing Research: The Bibliography helps readers understand the context in which your research was conducted and how it relates to existing knowledge in the field.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A resource for further research: The bibliography serves as a starting point for other researchers interested in your topic.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Demonstrate a deep understanding of the topic: An extensive and well-designed bibliography demonstrates that you have studied the subject in depth and are familiar with reputable sources.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;stages-of-working-with-the-bibliography&#34;&gt;Stages of working with the bibliography&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Working with a bibliography is a process consisting of several key steps:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Collecting Sources:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Identify Keywords: Start by identifying keywords related to your topic.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Search library catalogs and databases: Use library catalogs, scientific databases (e.g. JSTOR, Scopus, Web of Science), Google Scholar, and other resources to find relevant sources.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Study bibliographies in other papers: Review the bibliographies of other studies on your topic to find additional sources.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Critical evaluation of sources: Evaluate each source for its credibility, relevance, objectivity, and relevance to your topic.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;2&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Source Management:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using Bibliography Managers: Programs such as Zotero, Mendeley, and EndNote allow you to organize sources, create bibliographic entries, and automatically insert citations and references into the text. This greatly simplifies the process of working with the bibliography.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a database of sources: Create a database containing complete bibliographic data of each source (author, title, publisher, year of publication, DOI, etc.).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Record keeping: Make detailed notes about each source, highlighting key arguments, quotes, and your own thoughts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;3&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Citation in the text:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Choosing a citation style: Choose a citation style (for example, APA, MLA, Chicago, Harvard) and strictly adhere to it throughout the work. The citation style defines the rules for making references in the text and in the bibliography.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Correct citation design: Carefully follow the rules of citation style when making direct citations, paraphrases, and generalizations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Indication of authorship: Always specify the source of the information, even if you are paraphrasing it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;4&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Creating a bibliography:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Automatic Generation: Use bibliography managers to automatically create a bibliography based on your source database.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Manual review: Carefully check the automatically generated bibliography for errors and inaccuracies. Make sure that all entries match the selected citation style.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Alphabetical order: Bibliographic entries are usually arranged alphabetically by author&amp;rsquo;s last name.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;common-citation-styles&#34;&gt;Common citation styles&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are many citation styles, each with its own rules. The most common styles include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;APA (American Psychological Association): Widely used in psychology, education, and social sciences. Special attention is paid to the year of publication.
MLA (Modern Language Association): Widely used in the humanities, especially in literary studies and linguistics. The page number of the quotation is indicated.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chicago/Turabian: Used in history, philosophy, and other humanities. It offers two options: notes and bibliography, and author-date.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Harvard: A common author-date style used in various disciplines.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;IEEE (Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers): Used in engineering, computer science and other technical fields. Uses numbered links in square brackets.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;tips-and-best-practices&#34;&gt;Tips and best practices&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Start working with the bibliography at the early stages of research: Do not delay the creation of a bibliography until the last moment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be attentive to details: Even small errors in bibliographic records can undermine the credibility of your work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use bibliography managers: They greatly simplify the process of working with sources and help to avoid mistakes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Check your work: Check your bibliography carefully for errors and inaccuracies before publishing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Follow the instructions of your teacher or editor: If you are given specific instructions on how to create a bibliography, follow them strictly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Effective work with bibliography is an integral part of academic work. The correct design of references and bibliographic entries demonstrates your academic integrity, supports your arguments, and provides a valuable resource for further research. Using the tips and practices presented in this report, you will be able to successfully cope with the tasks associated with creating and using a bibliography.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Experience</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/experience/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/experience/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lightweight markup languages</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/post/md/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/post/md/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;lightweight-markup-languages&#34;&gt;Lightweight markup languages&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By learning Markdown, this simple and intuitive format, you can easily create attractive results. From PDF to web pages, your simple text file becomes a complex document. But Markdown isn&amp;rsquo;t the only game in town. There are a number of other so-called lightweight markup languages similar to Markdown, but with different feature sets. One of them is Asciidoc. If you like Markdown, but you&amp;rsquo;re looking for a bit more under the hood, it&amp;rsquo;s worth considering. Here are a few reasons why.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-is-a-markup-language&#34;&gt;What is a &amp;ldquo;markup language&amp;rdquo;?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A markup language is a set of codes that, when applied to plain text, allows you to add one or more of the following properties (among others):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Define the text&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Structure the text&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Describe the layout of the text&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Decorate the text&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One markup language that you encounter every day (unless you&amp;rsquo;re a hermit) is hypertext markup language, or HTML. Websites and applications that bring you news and show you your email are built, at least in part, with HTML markup that uses tags as a mechanism for marking up raw text content. For example, consider the following HTML snippet:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;body&gt; &lt;h1&gt;Introducing HTML&lt;/h1&gt; &lt;p&gt;Here is a paragraph in HTML... we know it&#39;s a &lt;strong&gt;paragraph&lt;/strong&gt; because the surrounding \&lt;p\&gt; tags define it as one.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, the &amp;lt; p&amp;gt; tag indicates that all subsequent text, up to the closing tag &lt;/p&gt;, is a paragraph. In this sense, he defines the text as a paragraph. But also pay attention to the tags&amp;hellip; they often serve to determine the layout of a web page, for example, how many fields are on the side of the screen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the &lt;strong&gt; tags will decorate the word &amp;ldquo;paragraph&amp;rdquo; in bold, and the &lt;h1&gt; tags can both mark the title (separate it from the surrounding text) and define a larger font.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem with some markup languages (HTML among them) is that entering these tags manually is a very tedious task. And with other languages like XML, tags and their attributes make up a larger part of the overall content than the text itself!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;enter-a-lightweight-markup-language&#34;&gt;Enter a lightweight markup language&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you wanted to take advantage of markup languages, for example by publishing an HTML page on the internet or converting a DocBook file to PDF so that it could be printed, you had to do one of two things. On the one hand, you can spend time learning these languages inside and out, writing them down manually, and then checking your work three times. Or you could invest the money in a tool that manages the complexity of it for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, some enterprising developers have come up with a third option. They created new markup languages that contained many (in some cases, most or all) of the features of their heavier counterparts, but significantly simplified the syntax. These &amp;ldquo;lightweight&amp;rdquo; languages include the familiar Markdown as well as Asciidoc, the Egc format in Org mode, and the Mediawiki syntax.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;lightweight-markup-languages-have-a-simple-syntax&#34;&gt;Lightweight markup languages have a simple syntax&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the distinguishing features of these languages is that their &amp;ldquo;tags&amp;rdquo; (such as these) must be intuitive. Let&amp;rsquo;s look at the previous fragment, this time written in Asciidoc.:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Introducing Asciidoc &amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;ndash; Where are the &lt;em&gt;paragraph&lt;/em&gt; tags? We dont need them&amp;hellip; Asciidoc is smart enough to realize this is a paragraph!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much more readable, no? Starting from the top, we can identify the title, as it is &amp;ldquo;underlined&amp;rdquo; with strokes. You could do this if you were writing by hand, just draw an underscore under the page heading in your notebook. There are also no paragraph tags — Asciidoc treats anything between two empty lines that don&amp;rsquo;t have any other markup on them as the &amp;ldquo;plain&amp;rdquo; text of the paragraph. Finally, the asterisks around the word &amp;ldquo;paragraph&amp;rdquo; are indicated in bold. Raise your hand if you did it in a text message to mean the same thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;each-has-one-or-more-corresponding-processors&#34;&gt;Each has one or more corresponding processors&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Heavy-weight markup languages usually have a special application for interpreting them. On the Internet, your browser and, possibly, a web server will turn the code into vivid web pages. For documents in XML format, it can be something like Microsoft Word, which reads and writes in DOCX format. (this is another dialect of XML). This way, you will never have to interact directly with the source of these documents, just the pretty facades that your applications show.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, documents written in light languages can be read by a person in their original form (another tenant), but only true nerds can consider them beautiful. To get a good result, you need to use a processor. These are applications that will consistently go through your markup and transform it into something else that looks good. The same projects that develop the language itself usually create a utility to use it. The Markdown project offers a Perl script with the same name, and the accompanying Asciidoc program is written in Python. In addition, other conversion utilities will include support for some of these languages. One such example is the excellent Pandoc, which will use Markdown, as well as lightweight tagging, restructured text, Mediawiki, and Org-Mode and convert them to PDF, DOCX, ODT, and others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a result, lightweight markup languages allow you to work with plain text, the most portable data format on the planet, but in the end they still produce beautiful results. Now that you are convinced of its advantages, which language should you choose? Markdown is undoubtedly the most popular and has its advantages (more on this later). But Asciidoc, in particular, is a worthy alternative. In the next section, we&amp;rsquo;ll look at a few reasons why.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;comparison-of-markdown-and-asciidoc&#34;&gt;Comparison of markdown and Asciidoc&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Asciidoc format was created to simplify DocBook, one of the most common formats when writing long (especially technical) texts. One of the requirements for fame is that it is a one-to-one translation, meaning there is a corresponding Asciidoc representation for each element in the DocBook. Below, we&amp;rsquo;ll look at some of the pros and cons of Asciidoc compared to Markdown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;###Asciidoc covers a superset of written elements
Markdown&amp;rsquo;s goal from the very beginning was to create a simple format for web writers. Thus, the writing elements it supports are aimed at automating the more time-consuming aspects of writing HTML (lists, for example, which require tags).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;or
in addition to &lt;li tags&gt; for each element).
Asciidoc also contains them, but it also offers more advanced DocBook elements such as warnings (such as &amp;ldquo;Note:&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;Info:&amp;rdquo; callout blocks) and complex table layouts. That doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean you have to use them all the time, but they will be there and available if you ever need them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;###Asciidoc is a single format
As Markdown&amp;rsquo;s popularity began to decline, some of its users began to experience some of the disadvantages described above. So these users started developing their own extensions to address these issues, such as the ability to add tables or footnotes/notes. Soon, many &amp;ldquo;flavors&amp;rdquo; of Markdown appeared, including (among others):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The flavor used by Github for the &amp;ldquo;Readme&amp;rdquo; files of the projects it hosted.
An &amp;ldquo;extended&amp;rdquo; version based on the PHP port of the original Markdown, with additional HTML-related features.
A flavor called &amp;ldquo;MultiMarkdown&amp;rdquo; that implements many of the features of writing longer forms, including citations, definitions, and cross-references.
As a result, your document may require elements that are not all covered by the same flavor. In contrast, Asciidoc does not suffer from the same fragmentation as Markdown currently does.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;###Asciidoc is aimed at a variety of publishing styles
Markdown is great for getting a blog post out of your head and onto the page quickly. But out of the box, it is not designed to structure longer works like a book. Asciidoc is designed for this, and one example is its &amp;ldquo;enable&amp;rdquo; functions. These operators allow you to include the entire contents of one file in another:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;include::somefile.adoc
This is not much different from how basic documents work in text editors. This allows, for example, to compose each chapter as a separate file, and then &amp;ldquo;include&amp;rdquo; them all in one file representing the book. When you process this &amp;ldquo;book file&amp;rdquo;, the result will be as if all the chapters were written directly into this document.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;###Markdown is enough for most users
Markdown covers all the basics for most users. For those who are just looking for a blog or typing some notes in text format, Markdown supports all the elements they will need. Cross-references don&amp;rsquo;t mean much to a user who just wants to create a simple note or web page. You could even use Markdown for longer work with simple layouts like roman&amp;quot; and combine them yourself at the end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;markdown-is-better-supported&#34;&gt;Markdown is better supported&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because Markdown meets the needs of a broader segment of users, it is ultimately better supported in terms of the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;WYSIWYG editors (as defined by those that at least provide a live preview) are more likely to support Markdown.
Online services such as the aforementioned Github are more likely to accept Markdown directly or through add-ons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although publishing systems such as static site generators are more likely to support Asciidoc with plugins, the fact that they support Markdown out of the box is almost self-evident.
Are you ready to try Asciidoc?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although Markdown is something of a de facto choice among lightweight markup languages, Asciidoc contains all the same elements, and then some. Additional information about Asciidoc takes some time to learn, as it can better prepare you for larger and more complex writing projects.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How was my week (March 17-21)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/post/last_week_17_03/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/post/last_week_17_03/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My week went well, except that I got sick. We have covered many interesting topics in Linear Algebra and Mathematical Analysis. They also spoke on humanitarian subjects. But the most interesting part was on Monday and Wednesday.
On Monday, the groups of the Translator Module performed songs and productions. The guys are great, even though I didn&amp;rsquo;t participate, I supported everyone.
And on Wednesday we had a couple on the Basics of military training. I picked up a gas mask for the first time and passed the standard on the first attempt: closing my eyes and holding my breath, I need to get the gas mask out of my bag and put it on in 7 seconds. I did it in 5.57.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>🧠 How was my week (April 07-13)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/post/last_week_07_04/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/post/last_week_07_04/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Last weekend we celebrated Mom&amp;rsquo;s birthday. We went to the countryside, and in the evening I gave her a huge delicious cake.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also wrote a Linear Algebra test. It&amp;rsquo;s a nightmare and a horror, but I hope everything will be okay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Tuesday, I went to my friend&amp;rsquo;s house to sort things out, as she had moved out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the IAB, we dressed up in a uniform with an armored vest. It was fun because it was heavy, and the teacher was showing me what to do.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>🧠 How was my week (March 24-28)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/post/last_week_24_03/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/post/last_week_24_03/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The beginning of this week was quiet. Studies, work, friends, rumors, gossip, investigations. But there was a little trip at the end. We applied for a visa and went to another city to be interviewed. All Thursday at the airport&amp;hellip; On Friday, we went to the consulate and sat there for several hours, but everything seemed to go well, we already had a plane home in the afternoon. And on the weekend, I have scotch and boxes waiting for me. I&amp;rsquo;ll be helping my friend with the move.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/projects/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/projects/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bash scripts</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/project/bash/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/project/bash/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this work is to study the basics of programming in the UNIX shell. Learn how to write more complex batch files using logical control structures and loops.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;task&#34;&gt;Task&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this work, it is necessary to study the work of bash scripts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is necessary to learn:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use logical control structures&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use cycles&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;getting-the-job-done&#34;&gt;Getting the job done&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Create the files ex1.sh-ex4.sh to do the work (Fig. [-@fig:001]).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;flex justify-center	&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;sh files&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /project/bash/image/1_hu_62c12213a67ee693.webp 400w,
               /project/bash/image/1_hu_d8c65d119a803da0.webp 760w,
               /project/bash/image/1_hu_aa52e410b2360bc.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/project/bash/image/1_hu_62c12213a67ee693.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;336&#34;
               height=&#34;17&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
{#fig:001 width=70%}&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Write a script for task 1 (Fig. [-@fig:002]).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;flex justify-center	&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;ex1.sh&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /project/bash/image/2_hu_68a068b5e3d5e5e8.webp 400w,
               /project/bash/image/2_hu_1761ca30c775c8f2.webp 760w,
               /project/bash/image/2_hu_f2fa9f3dfedffea5.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/project/bash/image/2_hu_68a068b5e3d5e5e8.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;235&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
{#fig:002 width=70%}&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Execute the file ex1.sh and we will check the correctness of the execution (Fig. [-@fig:003]).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;flex justify-center	&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;bash ex1.sh&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /project/bash/image/3_hu_2f4b021a560ae0f1.webp 400w,
               /project/bash/image/3_hu_55fecb822972abc1.webp 760w,
               /project/bash/image/3_hu_5bdaf187e431f80b.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/project/bash/image/3_hu_2f4b021a560ae0f1.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;235&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
{#fig:003 width=70%}&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Create ex2.c files for the C code (Fig. [-@fig:004]).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;flex justify-center	&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;ex2.c&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /project/bash/image/4_hu_933eec44dd1ae853.webp 400w,
               /project/bash/image/4_hu_7ec203116c35280d.webp 760w,
               /project/bash/image/4_hu_38a3e55877529014.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/project/bash/image/4_hu_933eec44dd1ae853.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;337&#34;
               height=&#34;23&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
{#fig:004 width=70%}&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Write the code in c (Fig. [-@fig:005]).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;flex justify-center	&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;ex2.c&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /project/bash/image/5_hu_c4efceb76e9da92c.webp 400w,
               /project/bash/image/5_hu_ebe7f55ab8e3098d.webp 760w,
               /project/bash/image/5_hu_a96cb174ee1f8061.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/project/bash/image/5_hu_c4efceb76e9da92c.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;242&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
{#fig:005 width=70%}&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Write a script for task 2 (Fig. [-@fig:006]).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;flex justify-center	&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;ex2.sh&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /project/bash/image/6_hu_7aca8e94ab4232c3.webp 400w,
               /project/bash/image/6_hu_abbcc36a4d874240.webp 760w,
               /project/bash/image/6_hu_ca11a5c4c9fa5bd3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/project/bash/image/6_hu_7aca8e94ab4232c3.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;652&#34;
               height=&#34;294&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
{#fig:006 width=70%}&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Execute the file ex2.sh and we will check the correctness of the execution (Fig. [-@fig:007]).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;flex justify-center	&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;bash ex2.sh&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /project/bash/image/7_hu_77a297be09e81903.webp 400w,
               /project/bash/image/7_hu_95e7648885775eb3.webp 760w,
               /project/bash/image/7_hu_a684f767b44a956b.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/project/bash/image/7_hu_77a297be09e81903.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;306&#34;
               height=&#34;80&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
{#fig:007 width=70%}&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Write a script for task 3 (Fig. [-@fig:008]).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;flex justify-center	&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;ex3.sh&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /project/bash/image/8_hu_acb4ff25da83c983.webp 400w,
               /project/bash/image/8_hu_a0486abe988887f9.webp 760w,
               /project/bash/image/8_hu_a13670b0353a280.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/project/bash/image/8_hu_acb4ff25da83c983.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;254&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
{#fig:008 width=70%}&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Execute the file ex3.sh and check the correctness of the execution (Fig. [-@fig:009]-[-@fig:010]).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;flex justify-center	&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;bash ex3.sh&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /project/bash/image/9_hu_4562ea798176f27f.webp 400w,
               /project/bash/image/9_hu_c4c3e256126a35e4.webp 760w,
               /project/bash/image/9_hu_c15c4f357f7489d4.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/project/bash/image/9_hu_4562ea798176f27f.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;149&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
{#fig:009 width=70%}&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;flex justify-center	&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;bash ex3.sh&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /project/bash/image/10_hu_9f0d895de11c48ef.webp 400w,
               /project/bash/image/10_hu_cc083e013ac9223.webp 760w,
               /project/bash/image/10_hu_4fee06dcf52165a6.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/project/bash/image/10_hu_9f0d895de11c48ef.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;149&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
{#fig:010 width=70%}&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Write a script for task 4 (Fig. [-@fig:011]).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;flex justify-center	&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;ex4.sh&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /project/bash/image/11_hu_7f9efa6afa6a089b.webp 400w,
               /project/bash/image/11_hu_1f284df0ea3b609e.webp 760w,
               /project/bash/image/11_hu_fd93a77bd41d39f6.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/project/bash/image/11_hu_7f9efa6afa6a089b.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;295&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
{#fig:011 width=70%}&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Execute the file ex4.sh and we will check the correctness of the execution (Fig. [-@fig:012]).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;flex justify-center	&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;bash ex4.sh&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /project/bash/image/12_hu_8197cf1c3c0cc14c.webp 400w,
               /project/bash/image/12_hu_55037ebfcf8dbad8.webp 760w,
               /project/bash/image/12_hu_e822e5613167cb95.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/project/bash/image/12_hu_8197cf1c3c0cc14c.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;295&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
{#fig:012 width=70%}&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;conclusions&#34;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this paper, we have studied the in-depth operation of bash scripts.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Version Control. Git</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/post/git/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/post/git/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;version-control-systems-general-concepts&#34;&gt;Version control systems. General concepts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Version Control Systems (VCS) are used when several people work on the same project. Usually, the main project tree is stored in a local or remote repository, to which access is configured for project participants. When making changes to the project content, the version control system allows you to fix them, combine changes made by different project participants, and roll back to any earlier version of the project, if required.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Classical version control systems use a centralized model that assumes a single repository for storing files. Most version control functions are performed by a dedicated server. The project participant (user) receives the required version of files through certain commands before starting work. After making changes, the user places the new version in the repository. However, previous versions are not deleted from the central repository and you can return to them at any time. The server may not save the full version of the modified files, but rather perform so-called delta compression — save only changes between successive versions, which reduces the amount of data stored.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Version control systems support the ability to track and resolve conflicts that may arise when multiple people are working on a single file. You can merge (merge) the changes made by different participants (automatically or manually), manually select the desired version, cancel the changes altogether, or lock the files for modification. Depending on the settings, the lock prevents other users from obtaining a working copy or prevents the OS file system from changing the working copy of the file, thus providing privileged access to only one user working with the file.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Version control systems can also provide additional, more flexible functionality. For example, they can support working with multiple versions of a single file, maintaining a common revision history up to the point of branching versions and their own revision histories of each branch. In addition, information is usually available about which of the participants made changes, when and what. Usually, this kind of information is stored in the changelog, access to which can be restricted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike classical systems, a central repository is not mandatory in distributed version control systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Among the classic VCS, CVS and Subversion are the most well—known, while among the distributed ones are Git, Bazaar, and Mercurial. The principles of their work are similar, they differ mainly in the syntax of the commands used in their work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;examples-of-using-git&#34;&gt;Examples of using git&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Git version control system is a set of command-line programs. They can be accessed from the terminal by entering the git command with various options.
Due to the fact that Git is a distributed version control system, a backup copy of the local storage can be made by simply copying or archiving.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;basic-git-commands&#34;&gt;Basic git commands&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s list the most frequently used git commands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Creating the main repository tree:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;git init&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Getting updates (changes) to the current tree from the central repository:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;git pull&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sending all changes made to the local tree to the central repository:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;git push&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;View the list of changed files in the current directory:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;git status&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;View current changes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;git diff&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Saving current changes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;add all modified and/or created files and/or directories:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;git add .&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;add specific modified and/or created files and/or directories:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;git add file_name&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;delete a file and/or directory from the repository index (while the file and/or directory remains in the local directory):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;git rm file_name&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Saving added changes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;save all added changes and all modified files:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;git commit -am &amp;lsquo;Description of the commit&amp;rsquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;save the added changes with a comment via the built-in editor:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;git commit&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;creating a new branch based on the current one:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;git checkout -b_name&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;switching to a certain branch:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;git checkout branch name_&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(when switching to a branch that is not yet in the local repository, it will be created and linked to the remote one)
sending changes to a specific branch to the central repository:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;git push origin_name&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;merging a branch with the current tree:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;git merge &amp;ndash;no-ff branch name&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deleting a branch:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;deleting a local branch that has already merged with the main tree:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;git branch -d branch_name&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;forced deletion of a local branch:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;git branch -D branch_name&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;deleting a branch from a central repository:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;git push origin :branch name&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;standard-operating-procedures-with-a-central-repository&#34;&gt;Standard operating procedures with a central repository&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The user&amp;rsquo;s work with his branch begins with checking and receiving changes from the central repository (at the same time, no changes should have been made to the local tree before starting this procedure):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;git checkout master&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;git pull&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;git checkout -b_name&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then you can make changes in the local tree and/or branch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After completing any changes to the project files and/or directories, they must be placed in the central repository. To do this, you need to check which files have changed to the current moment.:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;git status&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If necessary, we delete unnecessary files that we do not want to send to the central repository.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then it is useful to review the text of the changes for compliance with the rules for maintaining clean commits.:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;git diff&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If any files should not be included in the commit, then we mark only those files whose changes need to be saved. To do this, we use the add and/or remove commands with the necessary options.:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;git add …&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;git rm …&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you need to save all the changes in the current directory, then use:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;git add .&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then we save the changes, explaining what was done.:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;git commit -am &amp;ldquo;Some commit message&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sending the changes to the central repository:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;git push origin_name&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;or&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;git push&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
